<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon of the prouidence of God Preached at Paules Crosse, the 25. of October. 1607. By Iohn Pelling Bacchalaur of Diuinitie.</title>
            <author>Pelling, John, 1561 or 2-1621.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1607</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 81 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 27 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A09253</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 19567</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S114107</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99849335</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99849335</idno>
            <idno type="VID">14475</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A09253)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 14475)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1667:13)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon of the prouidence of God Preached at Paules Crosse, the 25. of October. 1607. By Iohn Pelling Bacchalaur of Diuinitie.</title>
                  <author>Pelling, John, 1561 or 2-1621.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 46, [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Nicholas Okes for Nathaniell Butter, dwelling at the signe of the Pide Bull neere S. Austins gate,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1607.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>The first leaf and the last leaf are blank.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:14475:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:14475:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A SERMON OF THE PROVIDENCE OF GOD.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Preached at Paules Croſſe, the</hi> 25. <hi>of October.</hi> 1607.</p>
            <p>By IOHN PELLING Bacchalaur of <hi>Diuinitie.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>PROVER. 4.13.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Take hold of inſtruction and leaue not: for ſhe is thy life.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>Nicholas Okes</hi> for <hi>Nathaniell Butter,</hi> dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling at the ſigne of the Pide Bull neere S. Auſtins gate. 1607.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:14475:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:14475:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT HONORABLE AND RE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LIGIOVS LORD, THE LORD EDWARD SEIMAVR EARLE OF Hertford, and to the right Honorable and <hi>virtuous Lady, the Lady</hi> Frauncis, Counteſſe of Hertford, Gods abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant graces and blesſings, for this life <hi>and for the life to come.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>Jght Honorable, my ſingular good Lord and Lady; your Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours both hauing from time to time ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedingly comforted, and encouraged me in my labours of this kind, J reſt aſſured, you will gladly accept and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tect to your vtmoſt, this ſermon of mine publiſhed, my good Lord, at your com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand. Whereas ſome of good ſort, and iudgment, moued your Lordſhip to put
<pb facs="tcp:14475:3"/>me to it, for a further good to Gods Church; and whereas alſo your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip out of your honourable and reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious care, procured the right reuerend father in God, the Lord Biſhop of London, my eſpecial good Lord, to require it of me; and ſeing hereupon his Lordſhip hath vouchſafed to peruſe it, and by his authoritie hath allowed it; hauing duely waighed all this, J profeſſe that I accompt, God hath had a directing and a work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing hand in all, and haue therefore o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beyed, leauing all excuſes, which I might probablie haue made: euen ſo Gods will be done. When a publique good in a mans calling, is likely to be effected, excuſes for priuate reſpects, in my conſcience haue no place.</p>
            <p>Had I but imagined in time, that it ſhould haue come to this at length, by
<pb facs="tcp:14475:3"/>Gods help it had beene better, and yet his goodneſſe it is, that it is no worſe: it is truth, and it is needfull, that J dare and do auouch for my part: to take it well, and to vſe it wel, may make it good and profitable, for your Honors firſt, and ſo for others, to whom God ſhall giue opportunitie and grace.</p>
            <p>J haue beene earneſtly moued to ſet it out as I preached it; of the words (I am ſure) I haue miſt very few, of the matter nothing.</p>
            <p>Your Honours are well knowne to to pray together, to heare ſermons to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, to receiue the communion the bleſſed body and bloud of Chriſt Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus, and that in your publique Pariſh-Church together; God grant more of your ſtate, for examples ſake, for their owne ſoules ſake, and for Gods glorie ſake, to do the like. If together
<pb facs="tcp:14475:4"/>alſo your Honors wil be pleaſed, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times to reade and conferre ſeriouſly of this diuine matter, heer conſecrated to your Soueraigne good, let me be blamed, and moſt ſeuerely cenſured, if you finde cauſe, to repent your well beſtowing time, and paines this way.</p>
            <p>The Lord God of mercies fill your noble hearts with heauenly graces, and powre vpon both your Honours, and all yours his richeſt blesſings, for his deare ſonne Chriſt Ieſus his ſake. Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don the <hi>25</hi> of Nouember. <hi>1607.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your honours moſt bounden and deuoted chaplaine, IOHN PELLING.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:14475:4"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>1. PETER. 5.7.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>Caſt all your care on him, for he careth for you.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Eing to prouide me for this time and place (right hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable, right worſhipfull, and welbeloued in our Lord and Sauiour Chriſt Ieſus) I haue with Gods direction (I truſt) ſetled vpon theſe words for my Text, which I haue heer read vnto you. I meane by Gods helpe, not to idle out a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny time in handling them, your faithfulneſſe in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring on your part, may with Gods bleſſing proue to you well worth the while. Obſerue therefore I pray you, the words, the doctrine, and the vſe. The wordes importe a commandement, and a reaſon to induce men to obey it. The doctrine, is the doctrine of Gods prouidence, which all that talke of, vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand not the truth, nor the depth of. The vſe is ſo manifold, and profitable, that any good man may be diuerſe wayes bettered by it; either he may be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed of that he knew not, or be reſolued in that he doubted of, or be put in minde of that he remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred not, or be perſwaded to that he affected not, or be comforted in his ſorrowes, or be moderated in his ioyes, or be incouraged in his wel-doing, or be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terred
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:14475:5"/>from euill: ſome, all theſe waies, ſome, by more then theſe may be ſingularly benefited, God in all duely ſerued, and his name glorified.</p>
            <p>The words importing the commandement are, <hi>Caſt all your care on him;</hi> the words inciting men to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey it, are theſe, <hi>For he careth for you.</hi> Next before my text we reade, <hi>Humble your ſelues vnder the migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie hand of God, that he may exalt you in due time,</hi> and ſo comes in my text, <hi>Cast all your care on him,</hi> it muſt be meant, on God, for <hi>he,</hi> that is God, <hi>careth,</hi> that is prouideth, <hi>for you,</hi> for you moſt eſpecially, and moſt beneficiallie, that caſt all your care on him.</p>
            <p>For men to caſt all their care on God, preſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth mens taking ſome care for themſelues, and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyeth that men ſhould not ouercharge themſelues with care, nor build vpon their owne, but vpon the care that God hath of them, who is better able to prouide for them, then they can for themſelues. So that to care, &amp; to care moderately, and to accompt it a mans beſt prouidence, to depend moſt vppon Gods prouidence, is that which we are here com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded, and incited vnto.</p>
            <p>Sith no man can care, in that meaſure or manner, nor relye in all his courſes vpon Gods care, Gods prouidence as he ought, either not knowing, or not duely conſidering what Gods prouidence is, we will by his aſſiſtance, plainely and truely deliuer the doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine, touching that great matter: plainely that it may be vnderſtood, truely, that it may be beleeued, and ſo by Gods grace alſo well applyed and vſed.</p>
            <p>In opening this doctrine, I muſt ſhew firſt what
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:14475:5"/>Gods prouidence is, 2. what things are ſubiect vnto it, 3. Gods manner of working by it. In the writings of the godly learned, we finde it thus deſcribed, <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uidentia Dei, eſt actio Dei externa &amp; temporalis, qua om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia et ſingula quae ſunt, conſeruat, et quae fiunt omnia &amp; ſingula diſponit ad finem quem ipſe determinauit, ſecun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum libertatem voluntatis ſuae, idque vt in omnibus et ſingulis glorificetur.</hi> The prouidence of GOD is an outward and a temporarie action of God, by which he doth preſerue all things that are, vniuerſall and ſingular, and doth diſpoſe of all things general and particuler, that are done, and doth determine the end of them, according to the libertie of his owne will, and that to this end that in all things generall &amp; particuler he may be glorified. And thus, <hi>Prouidentia Dei est eternum, et immutabile decretum Dei, de rebus omnibus et ſingulis, ad ſuos certos vſus et fines perducen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dis, ſecundum illum ordinem quem ipſe praefiniuit ad ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am gloriam.</hi> Gods prouidence is an eternall and an immutable decree of God, touching all things what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer, vniuerſal and ſinguler, to bring them to their certain vſes and ends, according to that order which God himſelfe hath appointed to his owne glorie.</p>
            <p>That theſe deſcriptions of the prouidence of God haue ſome diuerſitie in them, they muſt not bee thought abſurd; &amp; though they haue ſome ſembla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of oppoſition, they muſt not be thought falſe: for well lookt into they giue light one to the other, and well vnderſtood they nothing croſſe, but euery way ſtrengthen each the other. The diuerſitie that ſeemes is rather in words then in matter, the one peraduen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:14475:6"/>expreſſing more then the other, but both the truth. The oppoſition that ſeemes, is that Gods pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uidence in the former deſcription, is ſaid to be an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of God, an outward action, and temporarie; in the latter, that it is called an eternall and an immu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table decree of God. How can it bee an action of God, and a decree too, how temporarie and yet eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall and immutable?</p>
            <p>There are to bee conſidered in the prouidence of God, three degrees, <hi>praeſcientia rerum omnium, volun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tas rem quamlibet ad ſuum finem perducendi, et actualis eiuſdem voluntatis exequutio.</hi> God his foreknowledge of all things whatſoeuer, Gods will, to bring euerie thing to its certaine end, &amp; the actuall exequution of that his will. The two former of theſe his foreknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, and his will importe his decree, and that in God is eternall, and immutable: the latter the exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quution of his decree, and that is outward and tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porarie. Now ſome handling the prouidence of God, define it as it is a decree of God, ſome as it is his exequution of the ſame decree. They that han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle it as Gods decree, muſt needes ſet downe thoſe properties, which doe neceſſarily accompany his decrees, eternitie, and immutabilitie: they that han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle it as it is the exequution of the ſame decree, muſt needs ſet it downe as it is an action, and that tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porarie, yet both agreeing: for they that expreſly handle the action, preſuppoſe the decree, and they that expreſly handle the decree, imply the action: I, to make my treatiſe the more full, expreſſe both.</p>
            <p>For a ſumme of all, to ſhew what Gods proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:14475:6"/>is, conſider we yet, foure more particular de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees, which are, firſt <hi>Creatio rerum,</hi> the ſecond <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruatio rerum,</hi> the third <hi>Gubernatio rerum,</hi> the fourth <hi>Ordinatio rerum,</hi> the creation or making of things, the conſeruation or maintenance of things, the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>controuleable command and gouernment of things, the orderly ſetting and appointing vnto all things their ſeuerall and certaine ends. All theſe in order, are Gods prouidence, his decree eternall for all, and according to the ſame decree his actual exequuting all in time. Thus much as briefly and as plainly as I can poſſibly, to ſhew truely, and fully what all true chriſtians are to take Gods prouidence to be. Next what things are, they that are ſubiect vnto it?</p>
            <p>They are all mankinde; elect and reprobate, all mens actions, words and thoughts, good and bad: all courſes men take, all matters men take in hand, and all their euents, proſperous or croſſe: all creatures whatſoeuer, great and ſmall, all in all vniuerſal, ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial &amp; particular, are ſubiect vnto Gods prouidence they are according to his eternall, and immutable decree, in time begunne, continued, guided, and brought to their ends, to his glorie.</p>
            <p>Let vs take a view of <hi>Dauids</hi> 104. Pſalme, there ſhall we finde what things are within the view of Gods prouidence, that in wiſedome, that is, in his prouidence, God made, maintained, gouerned and ordained to ſet vſes and ends, the heauens ſpred like a curtaine, and light to decke all as with a glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious garment. The Moone to keepe her ſeaſons, the Sunne to riſe, and to know his going downe, the
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:14475:7"/>clouds caried about like chariots, and the winds as with wings, his Angels miniſtring ſpirits, the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dations of the earth vnmoueable, the deepe couered, the waters ſtanding ſometimes, and ſometimes fly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing at his rebuke; The voyce of his thunder to terri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie, the hils to go vp to, the valleys to go downe to, the ſprings ſent into the riuers, and the riuers to run among the hils, For the beaſts of the field to drinke and quench their thirſt. Graſſe brought foorth for cattle, and greene hearbe for the ſeruice of men, bread to ſtrengthen, wine to glad mans heart, and oyle to make him a cheerfull countenance, the day for him to labour in, and the night for him to reſt in, the ſoules to inhabit the ayre, and to ſing among the branches; the ſappie trees, the tall Cedars for birds to reſt in, the firre trees for the Storke, goates to haue refuge on hils, and to Conies in ſtony rocks; the Lyons one while to roare after their pray, and ſeeke their meate at God, another while to get them away together, and to lay them downe in their dens. The great &amp; wide ſea alſo with the creeping things therein innumerable both ſmall and great: God ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed the ſhips to paſſe them, and the Leuiathan, the greateſt fiſhes as Whales, and the like to make their paſtime in them. O Lord (ſaith <hi>Dauid</hi>)haw ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifold are thy workes, in wiſedome, that is in thy prouidence, thou haſt made them all, they all waite on thee, that is, depend on thy prouidence, things that need meate, to haue it in due ſeaſon, at the ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of thy hand, and thy filling them with good. Thus doth the glorious Maieſtie of the Lord en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure:
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:14475:7"/>Thus doth the Lord reioyce in his workes, in the workes of his prouidence, beginning, maintai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, governing them, and bringing them, to their due &amp; ſeuerall ends. Touching man himſelfe more particularly ſaith S. <hi>Paul,</hi> Act. 17. <hi>In him,</hi> that is in God, <hi>we liue, and moue, and hane our being,</hi> more par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly yet, the Prophet <hi>Dauid,</hi> as of himſelfe, ſo of euery good man liuing, in his 139. Pſal. <hi>O Lord thou haſt ſearched me out and hnowne me, thou knoweſt my downe ſitting and my vpriſing, thou vnderſtandeſt my thoughts long before, thou art about my path, and about my bed, and ſpieſt out all my wayes: For loe there is not a word in my tongue but thou O Lord knoweſt it altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, thou haſt faſhioned me behind and before, and layde thine hand vpon me, my reines are thine, thou haſt coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red me in my mothers wombe. I am fearfully, and wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully made, my bones are not hid from thee, though I be made ſecretly, thine eyes did ſee my ſubſtance, yet being vnperfect, and in thy booke,</hi> that is, in the booke of thy prouidence, <hi>were all my members written, which day by day were faſhioned, when as yet there was none of them,</hi> that is, none of them perfect. <hi>Whether then ſhall I go from thy preſence? If clime vp into heauen thou art there, If I goe downe into hell thou art there alſo, If I take the wings of the morning and remaine in the vttermoſt parts of the ſea, euen there alſo ſhall thy hand leade me, and thy right hand ſhall hold me, If I ſay peraduenture the darknes ſhall couer me, then ſhall my night be turned to day, the darkneſſe is no darkneſſe with thee, but the night is as cleere as the day, the darkneſſe and light to thee are both alike.</hi> All this is true of good men, ſo is it of bad men
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:14475:8"/>too. King <hi>Salomon</hi> in the 15 of his Prouerbs teacheth, that <hi>the eyes of the Lord in euery place behold the euill and the good.</hi> God is not properly ſayd to haue eyes but by an <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, after the manner of men. His eyes are taken for his all-viewing prouidence, in eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie place, Court, Citie and Countrey, publique and priuate, God beholdeth and obſerueth the euill and the good, men and women, actions and intents, whatſoeuer.</p>
            <p>Our Sauior himſelfe in the 5 of <hi>Matt.</hi> ſaith expreſly, that <hi>God maketh the Sun to ariſe vpon the euill and vpon the good, and ſendeth raine vpon the iuſt and the vniuſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I will conclude this point with an obſeruation of S. <hi>Chryſostome, Vt nauis ſine gubernatore.</hi> As a ſhip without a gouernour, is for no ſeruice. And as ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther noteth well, <hi>Vt corpus ſine anima,</hi> as a bodie without a ſoule can do nothing: <hi>Sic mundus,</hi> ſo the world could neuer be created as it was, nor continue as it doth, and hath done, nor be gouerned as it is, and hath bene, nor come to the appointed end it ſhall it ſelfe, and all things therein, <hi>Sine Dei prouidentia,</hi> without the prouidence of God. God worketh all things, according to the Council of his will: a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt all the reſt, all things concerning all men, and ſo vs heer from the higheſt to the loweſt. Thus much of thoſe things which are ſubiect to Gods prouidence.</p>
            <p>Now to the third point, the manner how God worketh in his prouidence, which we are to know &amp; acknowledge to be <hi>Vniuerſaliter, ſpecialiter, &amp; parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culariter,</hi> not generally only, but particularly too:
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:14475:8"/>ſecondly <hi>Immediatè &amp; mediatè,</hi> not immediatly al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes by himſelfe alone, but by meanes alſo many times, when it pleaſeth him: thirdly, <hi>Immutabiliter non mutabiliter,</hi> ſo neceſſarily, that it can be no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe then he will, and he doth nothing contin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gently: fourth and laſtly, <hi>Benè non malè,</hi> he worketh in euery thing well, in nothing ill.</p>
            <p>Not generally only, but particularly alſo, God had a worke with <hi>Ionas,</hi> when he charged him to go to Niniuie, when <hi>Ionas</hi> was ſhifting and ſhipt to go another way, God ſets a tempeſt to worke at ſea a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt that ſhip, God caſt the lot vpon <hi>Ionas</hi> to be caſt out, God prouided a Whale to receiue <hi>Ionas,</hi> and to ſet him ſafe on ſhoare. Againe, God charged him for Niniuie, guided him thither, prouided for him there. Gods hand in his prouidence, working particularly, is moſt euidently ſeene in this ſtorie.</p>
            <p>The like on <hi>Herod</hi> eaten vp with wormes for his pride; and on <hi>Pharaoh</hi> plagued, and confounded for his obſtinacy and hardneſſe of heart. The like on <hi>Iob,</hi> ſtrangely afflicted for his triall, &amp; more ſtrange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly crowned for his patience. The like on many other whom bookes do report, ſome notable particulars of; the like no doubt, on all men liuing, though men vſe to obſerue nothing but ſtrange matters that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fall them; but God is as particular in his ordinarie workes amongſt vs, as in his extraordinarie; ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie and extraordinarie to him are both alike.</p>
            <p>The next point is that God worketh in his proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence <hi>immediatè</hi> without meanes<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> yea againſt meanes, and ſometimes <hi>mediatè</hi> by meanes. With<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:14475:9"/>meanes, God created the world of nothing, he preſerued <hi>Moſes</hi> fortie dayes on the Mount without food, and the Iſraelites fortie ycares in the wilder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe without chaunge of apparell. In tempeſts at ſea many times, when men looke euery houre to be caſt away; In extremitie of ſickneſſe, when Phyſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and all giue a man off; In dangerous child<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>births, when women be at their wits end; in many deſperate extremities of this life, when wee ſee no meanes of helpe in the world, it is found diuerſe times, that GOD commeth in with his immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate helping hand and turneth tempeſtuous ſtormes to faire weather, deadly ſicknes to ſafe recouerie, moſt ſorrowfull trauels to ioyfull deliueries, the bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt iarres amongſt friends, to ſweete contentment, the greateſt neglect and fouleſt diſgraces (vnde er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued eſpecially) into higheſt accompt, and deareſt ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Kings hart</hi> ſaith <hi>Salomon</hi> in the 21. of the <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerbs is in the hands of the Lord as the riuers of waters, &amp; he turneth it whither ſoener it pleaſeth him.</hi> As Kings harts, ſo all mens elſe. <hi>Our God</hi> (ſaith <hi>Dauid</hi>) <hi>is in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, and hath done whatſoeuer pleaſeth him:</hi> as hee hath done, ſo doth he ſtill, and will doe, howſoeuer it plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth him, with meanes, or without meanes, or againſt meanes, meanes or no meanes to God, are both a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like; onely as in his prouidence he hath diſpoſed how things ſhall be brought to paſſe, ſo it muſt be. That he worketh againſt meanes, is the ſtrangeſt, but it is as true as the reſt. In the 14 of <hi>Exod.</hi> wee read that the ſea diuided for <hi>Moſes</hi> and the <hi>Iſraelites.</hi> In the 2.
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:14475:9"/>of <hi>Kings.</hi> 2. That the riuer of Iordan diuided for <hi>Elijah,</hi> and <hi>Eliſha.</hi> in the 10. of <hi>Ioſuah,</hi> That the ſunne ſtood ſtill for <hi>Ioſuah.</hi> In the 3. of <hi>Daniel,</hi> that the fire would not burne <hi>Shadrach, Meſhach</hi> and <hi>Abednego.</hi> In the 6. of <hi>Daniel,</hi> that the hungry Lions would not touch <hi>Dani<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>el.</hi> In the 12 of the <hi>Acts,</hi> that neither Iron chaynes, nor an Iron gate could hold <hi>Peter.</hi> In the 28. of the <hi>Acts,</hi> that a venemous viper could doe <hi>Paule</hi> no harme. If all the wicked of all the nations in the world, ſhould band themſelues againſt the Lord, and againſt his annoynted, our Prince, his prophets, his ſeruants, God can daſh them all, as it pleaſeth the Lord, ſo only come things to paſſe, bleſſed bee the name of the Lord.</p>
            <p>Now it followeth to be ſhewed, that God work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth by meanes, which I cannot declare better, then by ſhewing what meanes he vſeth in his workes: as firſt his Angels, that ſometimes appeare viſibly to men, as they did to <hi>Iacob</hi> in the 32 of <hi>Geneſis,</hi> when he was in his iourney, he calleth them the hoſt of God; ſometimes not ſeene at firſt but afterwards, as in the 2 of <hi>Kings.</hi> 6. <hi>Chap.</hi> the Prophet <hi>Eliſhas</hi> man at his Maiſters petition to God, had his eies opened, that he ſaw the mountaines couered with horſes &amp; Chariets of fire, which were Angels ſent for the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, and Gods peoples defenſe, againſt the mighty hoſte of the <hi>Aramites;</hi> ſometimes, and moſt common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly not ſeene at all to men, yet alwaies in a readines for Gods ſeruice, and his childrens preſeruation, as in the 18. of <hi>Matt I ſay vnto you</hi> (ſaith our Sauiour Chriſt) <hi>that their Angels alwaies behold the face of my
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:14475:10"/>father which is in heauen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As it was with thoſe little ones Chriſt there ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth of, ſo is it with ail Gods children. God keepeth angels to waite vppon them, though wee haue no proofe for euery one, one: yet haue wee for that which is as good or better. They are all, alwaies in ſuch a readines, at Gods commandement for mans good, that <hi>Dauid</hi> ſaith in his 34 <hi>Pſ.</hi> They alwaies <hi>pitch round about them that feare the Lord, to deliuer them.</hi> and the holy ghoſt in the 1. to the <hi>Hebrues</hi> teacheth, that they are all <hi>miniſtring ſpirits, ſent forth to miniſter for their ſakes which ſhall be heires of ſaluation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>When they are ſeene, they haue ſome ſhape gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen them for the time; that they are not ſeene, it is for that they are ſpirits, which are inuiſible to men; ſeene to men or vnſeene, God ſeeth them, and vſeth them, and they are his mightie meanes to preſerue and to deſtroy: The bad Angels and all, God vſeth to puniſh ſinners, and for the tryall ſometimes of the beſt men, as of <hi>Ioh.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Beſides Angels miniſtring ſpirits, God hath the heauenly bodies with their light, motion and iuflu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, which they haue all of God to worke vnder him, in the world, as in his Prouidence hee hath ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed. <hi>Moſes</hi> in the 1. of <hi>Geneſis,</hi> and <hi>Dauid</hi> in the 136 <hi>Pſal.</hi> teach vs, that God <hi>made the Sunne to rule the day, the moone and the ſtarres to gouerne the night.</hi> God himſelf in the 38 of <hi>Ioh,</hi> teſtifieth of a ſet courſe of the heauens, and of a pourefull rule of theirs o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer the earth; of the <hi>Pleiades</hi> and their ſweete in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluence, the ſtarres (as learned and godly men take
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:14475:10"/>it) which bring in the ſpring time. Of <hi>Orion</hi> and the looſing of his bands, a ſtarre which bringeth in winter, of <hi>Mazoroth</hi> and their times, the 12 ſignes: of guiding <hi>Arcturus</hi> and his ſonnes, which are like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe noted to ſignifie the north ſtarre, and thoſe thereabout.</p>
            <p>In the 9. of <hi>Ioh,</hi> wee reade of Gods counterman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding thoſe great Rulers of the world, the ſunne to riſe or not, and of God his cloſing vp the ſtarres as vnder a ſignet</p>
            <p>Beſides the heauens, God hath other his crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures too, as his effectuall meanes to the mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, gouernment and ordering of the whole. In the 2. of <hi>Hoſea,</hi> God ſaith, <hi>I will heare the heauens, and they ſhall heare the earth, and the earth ſhall heare the corne, the wine and the oyle, and they ſhall heare Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael.</hi> That is, God is the fountaine of all excellen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, of power and virtue to the heauens: the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uens ſhed downe their influences into the earth, the earth giueth nouriſhment to the corne, iuycé to the wine, fatneſſe to the oyle, all theſe are to inable and ſtirre vp man with gladneſſe, and cheerefu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, to ſerue vnder God in his prouidence, as he hath appointed.</p>
            <p>How men are this way, God his meanes may appeare by a viewe of mens ſtates in this land, publique and priuat, Their gouernment and their maintenance.</p>
            <p>In publique, the king in his kingdomes is imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately vnder God, ouer the Church and common wealth, he exerciſeth his ſoueraigne gouernment
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:14475:11"/>aſſiſted by his Council. Vnder the King, ouer the Church, are the Arch biſhops, and Biſhops, and the reſt of his Maieſties eccleſiaſticall gouernours.</p>
            <p>The Common wealth is to be conſidered as it is in peace, or as it may haue warres. In warres are noble men eſpecially to be generals, men of worth only to be captaines, commanders, and officers. In peace, Cities and great Townes are ordinarily go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerned by their Maiors, Aldermen, and others of the better ſorte; Countries abroade by the Peeres of the Land, the Iudges of the land, the Iuſtices, &amp; inferior officers vnder them.</p>
            <p>Priuat houſes, are either for learning, or for houſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keeping. In ſocieties of learned men, the heads and auncients, are to gouerne the yonger. In thoſe that ave for houſkeeping, and hoſpitalitie, are the huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band and the wife to rule their farnilie, children and ſeruants. In great mens houſes, chiefe officers in their places, are to command the reſt of the houſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold. I hus for gouernment.</p>
            <p>Now for maintenance; the King is to haue it roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally of his ſubiects, the Landlord rightfully of his tenents, the Churchmen liberally by the Church liuings, the Lawyers and Phiſitions duely by their fees, the Souldier is to liue on his pay, the Merchant by his trafficke, the husbandman by his flocke and tillage, the crafts man by his hands, the ſeruant by his wages, the poore and impotent, by almes and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neuolence. I cannot remember all, but you may ſee by theſe, how God doth vſe men, his meanes, for gouernment, and maintenance one of another.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:14475:11"/>
The next note is that God worketh immutably: firſt God is immurable himſelfe, the Holy ghoſt tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth it vs in the 1. of <hi>Iames, With God is no vari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ableneſſe nor ſhadow by turning.</hi> In his eſſence he is immutable, <hi>Malachi</hi> 3. <hi>I am the Lord I change not.</hi> In his decrees, the 19. of the Prouerbs, <hi>The Counſil of the Lord ſhal ſtand.</hi> In the execution of his decrees <hi>Eſai</hi> 14. <hi>The Lord of hoſts hath ſworne, ſaying, Surely like as I haue purpoſed ſo ſhall it come to paſſe.</hi> That nothing ſhall preuent him, or preuaile againſt him, the 27. of the ſame chap. <hi>The Lord of hoſts hath determined it, and who ſhall diſ mull it and his hand is ſtretched out and who ſhall turne it away.</hi> That this holds not in ſome places onely but in all, againe the ſame Prophet at the 26. verſe of the ſame 14. chapter: <hi>This is the counſil that is conſulted vpon the whole world, and this is the hand ſtretched out ouer all the nations.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now notwithſtanding all this, that we ſee the Sunne doth riſe and ſet, the Moone doth wax and wane, the ſea doth ebbe and flowe, the yeare hath winter and ſommer, that weather proues faire and foule, graſſe greene and withered, flowers freſh and fading, fruits ripe and rotten, that men in their minds, prone off and on; in their bodies, ſicke and healthie; in their ſtates, rich and poore; in yeares, yong and old; All theſe changes, and all elſe, argue not, that in God the creator there is <hi>mutatio volun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatis,</hi> but that God doth <hi>velle mutationem in creatura,</hi> God wils the change in the creature. The effects may be diuerſe, yea contrarie though the cauſe be one. The cauſe of all effects is God, in him there is
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:14475:12"/>no mutabilitie, though multiplicitie of power, God determineth ſecond cauſes. So that in reſpect of God, there is no caſualtie of effects, though there be varietie. Whatſoeuer God ordaineth in reſpect of God is neceſſarily that, that it is; it can be no other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe. God worketh immutably in his prouidence.</p>
            <p>The laſt note touching the manner of Gods wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king in his prouidence is, that he doth all things well, nothing ill. God commandeth in 1. Cor. 14. That in his houſe which is his Church, <hi>All things be done honeſtly and by order.</hi> As in the Church, ſo will God haue it in the comon wealth too, and as in pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique ſtates, euen ſo in priuat houſes alſo. In the ſame chap. 33. ver. <hi>God is</hi> ſaid <hi>not</hi> to be <hi>the author of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion. In the 9. to the Rom. there is a queſtion asked, whether there be vnrighteouſhes with God,</hi> the anſwer is in the ſame place, <hi>God forbid.</hi> It is true, that is in the 11. of Wiſdome, <hi>God hath ordered all things in mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, number and weight.</hi> And it is worthie to be no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted which is in the 1. of Gen. and ſo often repea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted at the Creation. That <hi>God ſaw that it was good,</hi> and when man was made and all, <hi>that God ſaw all that he had made, and loe it was very good;</hi> as it was with his workes of Creation then, ſo is it, and ſo hath it bene for his preſeruing and gouerning of things ſince, &amp; ſo will it be for his bringing things to their ſet ends alwayes. When God lookes vpon all the workes of his prouidence, loe they are all good; howſoeuer by mans degenerating, there is malig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie in the world, yet Gods worke in all (as he hath a worke in all) be things neuer ſo many and man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:14475:12"/>is good.</p>
            <p>If there were defect, diſorder, deformitie, or ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitie in any of Gods workes, his words in the 104 <hi>Pſal.</hi> touching this matter could not bee true, that <hi>The glorious Maieſtie of GOD ſhall endure for euer, the Lord ſhall reioyce in his workes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But ſomethings are ſo ſmall and vile, that they ſeeme vnworthy Gods gteatneſſe and excellencie: <hi>vt vermiculi, pulices, culices,</hi> wormes,, fleas and gnats; ſome things ſeeme for no vſe, no end, as ſnow, haile, and raine into the ſea, ſome things are ſo vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeaſonable and exceſſiue, that they rather doe hurt then good, as glutts of wette in ſeede time, or har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueſt, and ſcorching heate, and dryeth when graſſe ſhould ſpring and grow.</p>
            <p>Some things are ſo violent, and inordinat, that they ſeeme deadly miſchieuous, as fire, ſword, famin, peſtilence, ſhipwracks, inundations; ſome ſtrange, improbable, againſt all reaſon, prepoſterous, as wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked men to flouriſh, and inſolently to beare ſway, good men to go to wracke, and wrongfully to bee kept downe.</p>
            <p>Some ſo dolorous, ſo beyond all meaſure miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable, that thouſands ſeeme to haue iuſt cauſe to with the world rather had neuer beene, then one thing ſhould haue befallen, that if it had pleaſed GOD, might eaſily not haue bin; <hi>viz. Adams</hi> fal. What good hath man, what reioycing, what glory hath God by any of theſe, eſpecially the laſt? That God had his hand in all theſe wee cannot deny: but let vs take heede, wee be not ſo weake, or ſo hardie, for our lines
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:14475:13"/>ſo much as in a thought to tax GOD in his proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence for doing any thing amiſſe in all the world.</p>
            <p>For their ſatisfaction that are willing to learne, we will by Gods helpe giue anſweres to the doubts be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore caſt, and ſuch anſweres, as well taken, and well applyed, may giue reſolution to any doubt of this kinde that can be moued. Where <hi>Dauid</hi> beginneth his 148. <hi>Pſal.</hi> with <hi>O praiſe the Lord of heauen, praiſe him in the height.</hi> I pray you note, that hee goes on, recko<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning vp not onely the holieſt, the likelieſt, and the moſt glorious creatures, in heauen and earth, but e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen the verie vnlikelieſt that a man could imagine, the dragons that ſeeme and are miſchieuous; all depths, for all that ſome of them ſeeme and are to vs bottomleſſe; fire for all it is felt merciles; baile, ſnow and vapours, for all they ſeeme ſuperfluous; winde &amp; ſtormes for all they are tumultuous; the very beaſts and cattle, for all they are vnreaſonable; the creeping worme, for all it ſo contemptible; theſe all fulfill his word, that is, doe that in their kinde, which God by his ſecret operation inableth, and directeth them vnto: This, men ought to know and acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, and not to be ignorantlie, nor obſtinatlie con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentious.</p>
            <p>How can theſe things praiſe the Lord? <hi>Quum ip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſorum conſideratione laudatur Deus, ipſa laudant Deum.</hi> When by mans due conſideration of theſe thinges, God is praiſed, then do theſe things praiſe the Lord: <hi>Vos conſiderantes dracones,</hi> when you conſider the dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>g<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>os, take good notice of him that made the dragons, and when you doe wonder at the dragons, and at the
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:14475:13"/>greatneſſe of God that maketh the dragons, then doe the dragons out of your mouths, praiſe the Lord.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Quis diſpoſuit membra pulicis et culicis?</hi> who hath diſpoſed in order the partes or limmes of the flea &amp; gnar, they haue their proportion, they haue their life, their motion, they fly death, they loue life, they ſeeke after that they delight in, they ſhunne &amp; they auoyd, that which troubleth them, they haue ſenſe, they are quick and actiue in a motion that is kinde vnto them, <hi>Quis diſpoſuit ista, quis fecit ista? expaueſcis in minimis? lauda magnum.</hi> who hath made, who hath ordered theſe? art thou at thy wits end conſidering theſe little creatures? O giue praiſe to the almighty Creator, <hi>Quifecit Angelum in coelo, fecit vermiculum in terra:</hi> hee that made the Angel in heauen, made the little worme on the earth: did he make the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels to creepe vpon the ſlymie ground, or the worms to be glorious in the higheſt heauens? <hi>Diſtribuit ſedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus habitatores,</hi> he hath rightly diſtributed to inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants their dwellings, eternall habitations to immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal creatures, to corruptible creatures, corruptible places. <hi>Totum attende, totum lauda.</hi> Conſider all the order of Gods works, thou ſhalt ſee cauſe enough to praiſe God for all. All this moſt excellently hath S. <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> vpon the 148. Pſal. Againe the ſame god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie and learned father, <hi>Quare in mare pluit,</hi> why raines it into the ſea? <hi>Quaſi non ſint &amp;c.</hi> as though there be not (ſaith he) Gods creatures fiſhes there which are refreſhed &amp; cheriſhed with the raine water. <hi>At quare piſci pluit, et mihi nou pluit aliquando?</hi> why doth it raine
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:14475:14"/>to cheriſh the fiſh, when man lacks rayne ſometimes? <hi>vt cogites</hi> that thou mayſt think, thou art in the world as in a deſert, in a iourney, not at home; <hi>Vt amareſcat tibi haec vita,</hi> that this preſent life may grow diſtaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full vnto thee, that thou maiſt be deſirous of the life to come; or elſe that thou beeing a ſinner mayeſt be for thine amendment well corrected.</p>
            <p>But why doe lightning and Thunder beate vpon the mountaines to no purpoſe, and not ſtrike downe the theefe that robbeth there? that were ſome iuſtice; peraduenture God ſeeketh the conuerſion of that theefe. Euen thou thy ſelfe ſometimes (ſaith that good father) when thou ſchooleſt thy childe, doeſt beate the ground to make him afraide; but ſomtimes God ſtrikes the true man and lets the theefe go; what then? <hi>vndecunque mors pio bona eſt,</hi> howſoeuer a good man cometh by his end, he dies wel. And thou know<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>eſt if the wicked man repent not, he is reſerued for o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther manner of puniſhments in an other world, and thou little knoweſt the ſhame and torments which peraduenture hee ſhall abide before he goes out of this.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Quicguid ergo accoidit,</hi> whatſoeuer therfore happe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth otherwiſe then we would haue it, know, that it is not otherwiſe then God would haue it. It is accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to his prouidence, his order; and though we vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand not why things are made, why this or that is thus, and thus done, or diſpoſed, let vs attribute thus much to the prouidence of God, that it is not done without cauſe, nor without good cauſe; ſo ſhall we not blaſpheme.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:14475:14"/>
The concluſion is, <hi>Quum ceperimus diſputare,</hi> when wee beginne to make diſpute about the workes of God, why this is, and why that, hee ſhould not haue done this, or that was ill done, <hi>vbi eſt laus dei, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſti Halleluiah,</hi> where is thy praiſing the Lord, thou haſt loſt thy <hi>Hallettuah,</hi> thy praiſing the Lord. To this purpoſe very diuinely, one of the moſt godly and learned of all the fathers, S. <hi>Augustine</hi> vpon the 148. Pſalme.</p>
            <p>By this we may perceiue, that euen the ſmalleſt creatures in their kind magnifie their Creator, that that which ſeemes to the ignorant and inconſiderat needleſſe and vnprofitable, is indeed neceſſarie and beneficiall. And beſides, that when God by any meanes taketh away our prouiſion heer, it is to weane vs hence, or to chaſtice vs with want, for a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſing plentie; with warre, for abuſing peace; with ſickneſſe and weakneſſe, for abuſing health and ſtrength; with falſe friends, for abuſing true friends; with vnkindneſſe where we loue well, for our ingra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude to him, that loueth vs better: with croſſings in our buſineſſe, for our negligence in his ſeruice: and ye any of theſe, or all theſe are but gentle and louing corrections to his children, for their amend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: but with the graceleſſe and impenitent it is not ſo, let them ruffle it neuer ſo much for a while, bewate their end, plague vpon plague remaines for them, which they ſhall not be able to auoide; for God faileth not in his vncontrouleable prouidence, to ſee them payd that they haue deſerued.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:14475:15"/>
This perplexed <hi>Dauid</hi> at the heart, as we may read in his 73. Pſalme, when he ſaith, <hi>My feete were almoſt goue, my treadtings had well nigh ſlipt, and why? I was grieued at the wicked, I do alſo ſee the vngodly in ſuch proſperitie. and I ſaid then haue I clenſed my heart in vaine, and waſhed my hands in innocencie, all the day long haue I beene puniſhed and chaſtened euery morning. Yea I had almoſt ſaid euen as they, then ſhould I haue con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned the generation of Gods children: then thought I to vnderſtand this, but it was too hard for me, vntill I went into the ſanctuarie of God, there vnderſtood I the end of theſe men, namely how thou doeſt ſet them in ſlip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perie places, and caſteſt them downe, and deſtroyeſt them. O how ſuddenly do they conſume, periſh, &amp; come to a fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full end?</hi> That which <hi>Dauid</hi> learned in Gods ſanctu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arie, that he teacheth vs in this Pſalme. It is worth the remembring, and applying by your ſelues.</p>
            <p>We read in <hi>Geneſis</hi> a notable worke of Gods pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uidence, in <hi>Ioſeph,</hi> how God brought him to great honor and conforted him on euery ſide, how God prouided him to prouide for old <hi>Iacob,</hi> and all his. The meanes vſed were ſome very meane, ſome very vnlikely, and ſome almoſt impoſſible, yet all in Gods order direct, and by his power effectuall-Who would haue thought, that of a boy keeping ſheepe in Chanaan, one ſhould come to be the chiefeſt man vnder the King in Aegypt? that a dreame or two (a thouſand to one but ſo many idle fanſies) ſhould im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port and preſage matter of ſuch weight, conſequence and ſtate? that brethrens hatred ſhould be the way to brethrens loue? that to be bought and ſolde as
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:14475:15"/>a bondſlaue into a ſtrange Country, to be caſt and kept in priſon as a malefactor, ſhould be the way to libertie, to more then libertie, to a place of high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt honour in the Court, in all the Kingdome? So God wrought it and ordered it for <hi>Ioſeph.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And touching <hi>Adams</hi> fall, and ſo touching any actual ſinne, there is <hi>Actio,</hi> and there is <hi>Prauitas a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctionis,</hi> the action it ſelfe is not ſinne, God is the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor of the action, the deformitie or iniquitie of the action, that's ſinne, and that God is no author of.</p>
            <p>The godly learned illuſtrate this familiarly thus, The rider cauſeth the horſe to go, the horſe goeth lame; that he goeth, the rider is the cauſe, that he goeth deformedly lame, that's of the horſe and not of the rider. The ſoule of a man is it that cauſeth the body to moue; The body hath receiued ſome wound, or feſters with ſome old ſore, it moues, it moues deformedly, lamely, the motion is of the quickning ſoule, the lameneſſe is of the wounded or corrupt body.</p>
            <p>But touching the ſinne, is God no way the author of it? No way in the world, as it is ſinne: For firſt to be able to ſinne argues impotency, which cannot be found in omnipotencie, and to cauſe to ſinne is to bring forth more properly a defect, then an effect. But God hardened <hi>Pharaohs</hi> heart: not by making it hard that was not, but by denying him grace to mollifie his heart, which God is not bound to giue him, nor any man; But anſwer the Prophets words in the 3. of <hi>Amos, Shall there be euill in a citie, and the Lord hath not done it.</hi> I anſwer, that this is meant of
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:14475:16"/>
               <hi>Malum paenae,</hi> not <hi>culpae,</hi> of puniſhments which are iuſt, and which God iuſtly inflicteth vpon ſinners to their ſmart and griefe, not of any euill, that is, of any offenſe or fault that God commits or cauſes any to commit. What was <hi>Abſoloms</hi> in ceſt? It was both a ſinne and a puniſhmènt, a ſinne in <hi>Abſolom,</hi> a pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment to <hi>Dauid:</hi> the puniſhment was iuſt and of God, the inceſt ſinfull, ſhamefull, that was <hi>Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoloms.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Take with you this rule in our learning, in diui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie, which is a ſound rule in this caſe <hi>Cum eiuſdem effectus plures ſunt cauſae, aliae bonae, aliae malae, effectus ille reſpectu bonarum cauſarum, bonus eſt, reſpectu vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioſarum malus.</hi> Admit there concurre diuerſe cauſes to one effect, that effect in reſpect of good cauſes ſhall be a good effect, in reſpect of vitious cauſes e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill. But God at leaſt permitteth ſinne as it is ſinne, or he doth not permit it; If he permit it not, how can it be? If he permit it, either he doth it with, or againſt his will: If againſt his will, how then is God omnipotent, that he cannot ſtop it? If with his will, how then is God all goodneſſe, that he will not ſtop it? If it be neither with nor againſt his will, but that he lets things go, neuer heeding them off or on, where is his prouidence that workes ſo carefully, and ſo effectually in all?</p>
            <p>I anſwer. Firſt, that Gods will is conſidered as it is ſometimes <hi>occulta</hi> ſecret, ſometimes as it is <hi>ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſta</hi> reueiled, alwayes as it is <hi>iuſta,</hi> iuſt.</p>
            <p>Secondly, that ſinnes are not meaſured by the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret will of God at all, but by his reueiled will,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:14475:16"/>which is his lawe; and therfore though we graunt a permiſſion in Gods ſecret wil, of that which is ſinne, yet God in that, willes nothing as ſinne, for as no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing can be done againſt his ſecret will, ſo no ſinne is meaſured by it, and therefore nothing is to be cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led ſinne with reſpect vnto it. This beeing certaine, then ſtill I ſay, that ſinne as it is ſinne, is not of God.</p>
            <p>But how can any thing be againſt Gods reuealed will, and not bee againſt his ſecret will, they beeing one? as they are diuerſly conſidered; to be ſecret and to be a reuealed are diuerſe conſiderations; in one &amp; the ſelfe ſame reſpect, nothing can bee againſt the one, and not againſt the other; but in diuerſe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects it may be, one thing may be <hi>Contra voluntate<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> reuelatam,</hi> againſt Gods reuealed will, his law, it bee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the rule of right and wrong, to the creature, the meaſure of ſinne: and yet not <hi>praeter voluntatem occul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tam</hi> not beſides Gods ſecret will, it beeing not to the creature any rule of right or wrong, but it reſpecteth euery thing whatſoeuer, <hi>ſub ratione boni,</hi> as it is good, as it is a mean to Gods glorie, and ſo <hi>reductiue,</hi> what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer it be, it is good.</p>
            <p>And further we are to know &amp; acknowledge that to permit that which is vnexcuſably ſinne in man, is not ſinne in God, fo we haue an other infallible rule in diuinitie, <hi>Quum is qui permittit, inhibendi poteſlatem habet abſque vlla obligatione, vt &amp; is cui permittitur agendi abſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> vlla coactione, Actus vtrobique eſt volunta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius, in priore abſque culpa, in poſteriore abſque excuſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tione,</hi> when he that permits hath power to forbid, &amp; is free from any tie to permit or not to permit, to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bid
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:14475:17"/>or not to forbid, and that he which is permitted hath power to doe without conſtraint, the action in both is voluntary, in the former that is in GOD the creator, without ſinne, in the later the creature man or Angel without excuſe. But how can GOD any way permit ſinne, and yet bee no way the author of ſinne? fiſt <hi>ſine approbatione</hi> without approuing it, 2. <hi>denegatione gratiae,</hi> by denying the partie grace, and leauing him to himſelfe, as God may doe if he will, &amp; it is therfore iuſtly done becauſe he doth it, 3. <hi>pec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catum determinando ne latius ſerpat,</hi> by limiting it, that it ſhall not go ſo farre as the tempter, or the ſinner would. Laſtly <hi>ordinando,</hi> as in <hi>Adams</hi> fall, the Diuel wrought moſt ſubtilly <hi>tenta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>do,</hi> man wrought actual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>peccando,</hi> God wrought prouidently <hi>dirigendo;</hi> Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than in malice tempted man to ſinne to deſpight God, man in folly ſinneth to pleaſe himſelfe, God in his prouidence directeth al, to the ſhewing of mercie by ſending his ſonne to redeeme ſome, and to the ſhewing of his Iuſtice in bringing confuſion on them that dye without redemption. Gods mercie and his iuſtice, tend and<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> worke both to Gods euerlaſting glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, which is the maine and moſt bleſſed end of all.</p>
            <p>Yet had it not beene better, that <hi>Adam</hi> had beene created better, that as he was created <hi>bonus</hi> good, ſo he had beene created <hi>immutabiliter bonus,</hi> immutably good? I anſwer no, for firſt looke how God created him, that was beſt, &amp; therefore beſt, becauſe he cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ated him ſo: then to be <hi>immutabiliter bonus,</hi> immuta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly good is an eſſential propertie of God. It were ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſimple, for any man to imagine that the creature
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:14475:17"/>man, or Angel, ſhould be made the creator, God.</p>
            <p>To conclude this point, our God with whom we haue to doe, is the Loxd, <hi>dominus primus, ſupremus,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>liberrimus.</hi> The firſt, the higheſt, ſole Lord of himſelfe, and moſt abſolutely free; the firſt before all in eternitie: the higheſt aboue all in infinite Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie: ſole of himſelfe, he depends on none, but all of him; he is abſolute at his owne libertie, his will a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone is an abſolute warrant for him to doe withall vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der him whatſoeuer he will, to make or to deſtroy, to make poore or rich, to exalt high, or bring lowe, to reiect or ſaue, at his free pleaſure, he is ſubiect to no controwle or check, ſay he, do he, decree he, execute he, what hee will, where, when, and on whomſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer.</p>
            <p>And if any man will, let him with any thing a good minde looke into any the workes of God, any one, the vnlikelieſt to mans reaſon, yet ſhall he finde it without defect, deformity, diſorder, or any iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, if he conſider it wholie and intirely togethe; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare the beginning with the end, conſider the means determinatly working, from the beginning to the end, you ſhall finde that he hath done, and doth all things well. As in the working of <hi>Arras,</hi> tapiſtry or the like, in a loome or frame, you ſhall lee heer a leg and there an arme, and yonder a head, a very imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect peece of worke, if there were all: but when it is finiſhed, euery part brought in, as it is at laſt in due proportion, then behold the cunning head and hand haue brought it to an excellent worke: So conſider Gods workes, not piecemeale, but wholly &amp; entirely
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:14475:18"/>part not the beginning from the end, nor theſe from the meanes where God vſeth any.</p>
            <p>Conſider <hi>Dauids</hi> adulterie and murther, <hi>Peters</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nialls and curſing, but withall the harty repentance of them both. Conſider faire <hi>Abſolons</hi> death, but with all his treaſon; <hi>Sampſons</hi> eies cruelly pulled out by the Philiſtines, but withall his blind luſt to lewd <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lilah.</hi> Conſider the little children torne in pieces by beares, but withall their mocking of Gods Prophet. Conſider <hi>Adams</hi> fall, but withall Chriſt promiſed. Conſider Chriſts ignominious death, but withall his glorious reſurrection. Take one thing with another in all Gods workes, I ſay to any man as <hi>Auguſtine</hi> ſaith, <hi>attende totum, lauda totum,</hi> conſider the whole, &amp; it will well appeare, that God is to be praiſed, that God hath done and doth his parte, in euery parte a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Eliphaz</hi> in the 5. of <hi>Iob</hi> diſcourſeth the whole chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter through of this argument, of gods working in his prouidence, eſpecially vpon man, the laſt of his words are, <hi>loe thus haue we inquired of it, and ſo it is, heare this, and know it, for thy ſelfe;</hi> we haue enquired as hee did at God, ſo it is as from God you haue heard, you haue heard it all, let euery man know it for himſelfe, that is, let euery man make a good vſe of that, which tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching this great matter he hath heard, for he is now vnexcuſably if he know it not.</p>
            <p>Firſt therfore you muſt accompt this doctrine true, neceſſary, profitable and euery way a good doctrine. Being true as it is infallibly true, then not to belieue it, is erroneous, to argue againſt it, is impious, to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:14475:18"/>in diſcourſe about it, without any care or pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, to ſettle poſitiuely in it, is vanitie prophane cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rioſitie, the way to blaſphemous <hi>Atheiſme.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It being alſo a neceſſarie doctrine, then to be care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe whether euer one heare of it or noe, let God in his workes do, or in his word ſpeake what he will, not to accompt it concernes a man, but let the world goe which way it will, neuer to trouble ones head about ſuch matters, this is dull ſtupiditie, neere to a dead fearing of the confcience, neere to a reprobate ſenſe. It is ſo profitable a doctrine, that well learned and well vſed, it informes a mans vnderſtanding with the knowledge of God and himſelfe; it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formes the will to religious reſolutions, it reformes the courſes of a mans life, to chriſtian obedience, it armes a diſtreſſed and an iniured man with patience, it humbles a man full of proſperitie, that he burſt not with pride; it tempers a man giuen to his laſciuious and luxurious appetite that hee ſhall abſtaine: it cooles, nay it quenches a mans fierie and ſudden fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, that he ſhall do no miſchiefe: it pacifieth ones deepe conceiued diſpleaſure, and otherwiſe impla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cable offenſe taken, that a man neither workes nor meditates reuenge; it makes men make a conſcience of their doings, for their gaine, for their delight, for their preferment, for any way hauing their will, their purpoſe. It makes men remember whence they came, conſider where they are, what they doe, and whither they ſhall; it keepes men the more in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent that they doe no harme; It makes men the more warie that they take no harme; it teacheth
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:14475:19"/>men how to liue well, and how to die well, which is next to eternall felicitie, line he poore or rich, in high or low eſtate, die he in his flouriſhing or decre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pit age, of what diſeaſe, by what meanes, at home or abroad, at ſea or land, when, where, and how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer.</p>
            <p>A doctrine ſo true, ſo neceſſarie, ſo profitable, muſt needs be good; Why then ſhould any miſlike it? no man liuing can diſproue the truth of it, nor a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoide the neceſſitie of it, nor do well without the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit of it; yet ſome like it not, or if they like it, they like it in part not wholly.</p>
            <p>Some like not to be alwayes within the view of Gods prouidence, to be in his eye-ſight, in his aw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full preſence ſtill: ſome like Gods prouidence to be maintained by it, but not to bee gouerned by it. Some will not ſay but they like himſelfe, but they are not contented with theſe and theſe his meanes, they will try their owne deuiſes, though indirectly to mend their meanes. Some like proſperity mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uelouſly well, but they are made for no croſſings. Some like their beginning and their courſe hitherto, vp and down, one time with another, but they would heare ſome of no end, ſome of no ſudden end, and ſome of no lingring death. Some profeſſe they are pleaſed with Gods gouernment, but would none of the kings ſupremacie. Some like not the Iudges of the land, nor the lawes of the land, not the execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of iuſtice, alls too ſharpe, too ſeuere. Some beare the King his ciuill gouernment very gently, but cannot away with his eccleſiaſtical gouernme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:14475:19"/>
Some miſlike one thing and ſome another, ſome would haue this alteration in the ſtate, and ſome that; but he ſinnes damnably in abuſing the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of Gods prouidence, that wholly or in part approues not that, which God hath ſo well eſtabli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed for good: that beleeues not, that eſteemes not, that receiues not the doctrine of Gods bleſſed pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uidence, that ſubmits not his Iudgment, his actions, himſelfe vnto it, to be rectified by it, as euery way good.</p>
            <p>A ſecond general vſe is to keep Gods order in preferring one thing before another, and in ioyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſome things with other. Men ought therefore to preferre God before meanes, heauen before earth, the ſoule before the body, reaſon before affec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, publique matters before priuate, religion be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore policie, Gods glorie before mans. Men ought not prepoſterouſlie to inuert Gods order; nor in any wiſe to put thoſe things aſunder, which God hath appointed to go together; as faith and workes, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit of lawes and obedience to lawes, a good ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate and a good man, deſert and rewarde, mercy and truth, righteouſneſſe and peace, knowledge and conſcience, thrift and a true ballance, delight and temperance, aduerſitie and patience, wrong taking and charitable forgiuing, honour and hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>militie, wealth and beneficence: benefites receiued, and thankfulneſſe, any charge in the Church or common wealth, in publique or priuate, and ſaith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe; good preparation in time, and an happie end at laſt.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:14475:20"/>
A third general vſe is, to account this doctrine not a matter of ſpeculation, but of practiſe, the more we know to do the better, the more we learne of Gods prouidence oner vs, the more prouidently to line all our dayes vnder him; which is, he careyng for vs, he prouiding for vs, our caſting all our care on him, in all our prouidence, our depending vpon him. To caſt all out care therefore on him, is to care as he commands and not otherwiſe, to care for that he allowes and for nothing elſe, to care that we vſe good meanes well and not amiſſe, and to care for ſucceſſes ſo, as that we leaue them wholy to God. This is rightly to caſt al our care on him, and this is to be rightly prouident.</p>
            <p>To which there are required three things, <hi>memoria praeteritorum, cognitio preſentium, precognitio futuro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum.</hi> remembrance of things paſt, knowledge of things preſent, and foreknowledge of things to come. Theſe things ſeeme hard, (as to ſome any good things will) eſpecially the laſt; now euery man would be accounted a man of iudgement, them I hope he remembers things paſt, compares them with things preſent, and obſerues correſpon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dencies, dencies, and differences, he cannot then but fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſee many conſequences. Like cauſes are like to bring forth like effects. He that forgets all paſt, neglects all preſent, foreſees, forecaſts, preuents, prouides, nothing to come, may wanton it a while, but ſhall want at laſt; may ſtate it awhile, but muſt ſtoope at laſt: may haue his full deſire a while, but ſhall haue his due deſerts at laſt. For laſciuious prodigaltie
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:14475:20"/>to bring penurie, aſpiring pride, to haue a fall, ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full beginnings and lewd courſes, to haue ſorowfull and ſhamefull ends, it hath bene, ſo it is, &amp; will be. It is a blinde wretched and an vnpardonable folly, for any man to be partiall in his owne particular, to looke carefully neither backe, nor forth, to be only for the preſent, and but in conſider at in that too. As God will haue a man to be, not careleſſe, ſo doth he not allow all caring: They in the 4. of the Prou. that <hi>cannot ſleepe except they haue done euill,</hi> are like inough to be full of care. <hi>Ahab</hi> in the 21 of the firſt booke of Kings taking his bed, &amp; leauing his meat, either of anger, or griefe, or greedines (a deuouring ſickneſſe of theſe dayes too) &amp; all for <hi>Naboths</hi> vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yard, had his head, and hart no doubt full of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexing cares; and <hi>Ieſabell</hi> his wife<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> that cheered him vp and compaſt the matter with forgerie and bloud, ſhe had care inough, but ſuch caring God likes not. The dogs lickte vp the bloud of <hi>Ahab</hi> at laſt, and of <hi>Ieſabell</hi> too; they gnawed her bones, there could nothing of her be found, when they came thinking to burie her, but her skull, her feete, and the palmes of her hands. Neither al their care, nor al their great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe could keepe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> from the curſe of God brought vpon their heads, for their bloudy purchaſe. No tyrannous oppreſſors beating their braines, how they may draw, ingroſſe, incloſe all to themſelues; no ſhifting companions that liue by their graceleſſe wits, muſt thinke that God takes charge of their cares, to bleſſe them with ſucceſſe to their deſires. Our prouident man is an honeſt man, that couets
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:14475:21"/>not another mans, that cares and prouides to haue for himſelfe and his, bur without wronging of any.</p>
            <p>Beleeuing and righteous <hi>Abraham</hi> in the 22. of <hi>Geneſis,</hi> when <hi>Iſack</hi> put out a word to him as they were going together, <hi>Behold my father, the fire and the wood, but where is the Lambe? Abraham</hi> being reſolued whatſoeuer became of himſelfe, or his ſonne, that Gods commaundement muſt be obeyed, his promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes would be performed, and not being able to reach by any reaſon to the poſſibilitie and ſecrecie of Gods worke in this, he anſwers, <hi>My ſonne, God will prouide,</hi> as if he had ſaid, we muſt depend vpon Gods proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, that muſt ſatisfie thee and me, God knoweth what he hath to do, he ſeeth what we do, God will prouide for vs, doing that which he commaunds. Let vs go on our way, and caſt all our care on him, for he careth for vs. So let any good man reſolue, that what God commands muſt be done; a man ſo reſoluing alwayes, be ſees no other but it will go hard with him ſometimes; But let God haue his ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice in thine heart, reſolue aboue all things in the world for his ſeruice, and God will prouide for thee, both to be able to ſerue him, and to prouide for thee and thine in his meaſure, in better ſort it may be for the particular, then thou canſt nowe thinke.</p>
            <p>A man may care to haue about him, to leaue be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind him, this is prouidence; but he muſt haue a care that his gathering be without doing wrong by violence or fraude, this is obedience; both muſt goe together where men caſt all their care
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:14475:21"/>on God, and looke that God ſhall care for them.</p>
            <p>But men ſhall be tempted to the contrarie. In the 4. of <hi>Matthew,</hi> and in the 4. of <hi>Luke,</hi> the Diuell is ſayd to tempt our Sauiour Chriſt himſelfe ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing him at an aduantage (as he thought)in this world, in humane nature, and at a time (after fortie dayes faſting) hungrie, ſubiect vnto Gods proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, he thought to make him ſinne againſt it, as either to truſt wholly to meanes and thoſe indirect <hi>(make bread of ſtones)</hi> or to truſt wholly vpon Gods prouidence without meanes (<hi>Caſt thy ſelfe downe hence</hi> from this pinnacle) or the end of all Gods glorie to ſet it at nought; ſhewing him all the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes of the world (if it were but in a viſion that's all one) <hi>H ſhewed them him in the twinckling of an eye, and ſayd vnto him, all this power will I giue thee, and the glorie of theſe kingdomes, for that is deliuered vnto me, and to whomſoeuer I will, I giue it. If therefore thou wilt worſhip me, they ſhall be all thine.</hi> Our Sauiour ſhakt him off at laſt, and it was time, <hi>Hence from me Satan.</hi> If our Sauiour Chriſt had not beene euen prouidence it ſelfe, he had hardly preuented Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tans moſt miſchieuous ſubtiltie. Heere was euery way layde for him: Had hee beene coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tous, heere was a <hi>world:</hi> had hee beene ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious, here were <hi>all the Kingdomes of the world:</hi> had hee beene tyrannous, heere was <hi>all</hi> the <hi>power</hi> of thoſe kingdomes; had he beene popularly vaine-glorious, here was the <hi>glory</hi> of all the power of the kingdomes of the world, not ſhewed him only
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:14475:22"/>but offered him; not driuing him out with lingring expectation, <hi>all</hi> is offered him at once: not at any hard rate, but of free gift: and leſt there ſhould be doubts made, that Satans offer was greater then he was able to performe, he ſaith it is all his owne, <hi>deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered</hi> him, and leaſt it ſhould be obiected, it was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuered him to keepe and not to do away, he ſaith it is his to <hi>giue,</hi> if he <hi>will:</hi> and leaſt it ſhould ſeeme re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrained to ſome one, he addeth, <hi>To whomſoeuer I will, I giue it.</hi> Leaſt it ſhould be thought there were too many, that would looke for it, he ſaith, <hi>They ſhall be all thine:</hi> and leaſt this ſhould be condemned for pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digall follie, there is a ſoucraigntie reſerued, <hi>If thou therefore wilt worſhip me:</hi> who would ſtand for ſo ſmal a matter, when his gaines &amp; aduancement ſhold be ſo infinit? the whole world could affoord no more, and who would wiſh to haue it all for leſſe? All this, nay halfe this, to a man not very prouident had been inough to haue made him forget all matter and ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remony of Gods glorie. But by that we haue heere learned, we find in the offer to be no good intended, the condition impoſſible ſo much as with ſafetie, the title Satan pretended to haue, was falſe; the deliuery neuer made to him, the gift was by no right in him, the ſhew of all was but a ſnaring deuiſe, the offer of earthly kingdomes, to make him looſe his heauenly kingdome, the offer of power on earth, but to ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſe him with the power of hell, the offer of ſo great glorie, but to bring vpon him the more ſhamefull confuſion. That labour of Sathans was loſt, he pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uailed not againſt our Sauiour.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:14475:22"/>
But doth he now ceaſe? is he not as ſubtile, as ſtro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g, as ſtirring, as tyrannous as euer he was? is it not his ſolliciting ſtill to haue men miſtruſt Gods proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, and build onely vpon meanes, be they neuer ſo indirect? or preſume vpon Gods prouidence, &amp; ſo tempt God, contemning his meanes? or to forget gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing God his glorie, and therein to giue Sathan a worſhip? and thereby men to looſe their part in Chriſt Ieſu? know we not that he is called in the 2. to the Corinth. 4. <hi>the God of this world?</hi> in the 12. of <hi>Iohn the prince of this world?</hi> in the 2. Chapter of the Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle to the <hi>Ephe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> the prince that ruleth in the aire, the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit that worketh in the children of diſo bedience?</hi> in the 12 of the Reuelation, <hi>tho read dragon?</hi> in the 3. of Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſis, <hi>the ſerpent?</hi> in the 13. of Matth. <hi>the enemy?</hi> in the 8. of Iohn, <hi>the father of lies &amp; a murtherer?</hi> in the next verſe after my text, <hi>a roaring lyon ſeeking whom he may denoure?</hi> doe wee not learne by all theſe ſcriptures that he is ſet to deſtroy man, bodie and ſoule? It is he that cauſeth ſchiſme, hereſie, and hypocriſie, in the Church; diſorders, and rebellions in Common wealths; ambition in Princes Courts; corruption in Magiſtrates, refractarie diſobedience in ſubiects; looſenes in youth, peeuiſh moroſitie in old age; gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dineſſe and oppreſſion in the rich, vnthankfulneſſe, impatience and ſhifting in the poore &amp; needie; ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtition in the ſimple, prophaneneſſe in the witty; diſcord in families, falſhood in truſt and friendſhip, abuſe of meates and drinkes, pride in aparell, exceſſe of eaſe and ſportings, impediments to well doing in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citements to ill; and he taketh his aduantage, by fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:14475:23"/>tempting ſuggeſtions inwardlie, to euery hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mor, and by preſenting pleaſing obiects outwardly to ſerue euery mans appetite.</p>
            <p>Sathan is he whome <hi>Salomon</hi> ſpeakes eſpecially of in the beginning of the 23. of Prouerbs, <hi>When thou ſitteſt to eate with a Ruler, conſider diligently what is ſet before thee, and put the knife to thy throate, if thou bee a man giuen to thine appetite: be not deſirous of his dainty meates, for it is a deceiueable meate.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Let Sathan make neuer ſo faire ſhewes, his end is ſinne and deſtruction; any thing a prouident man will ſtriue hard with himſelfe rather then come to that. One would thinke it impoſſible, that any, whome Sathan entertaines with his ſweeteſt with his moſt delicious ſinnes, if the partie knew he would bring him to vncureable wounds, knowne to come of no honeſt cauſe, that he would bring ſtinking rot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenneſſe vpon his filthy hairy, or filthier vnhairy ſcalp he would neuer haue the heart, (one would thinke) to goe on ſtill in his wickedneſſe. It is withall the diuels allurements, though he would not be miſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted, as with that wine <hi>Salomon</hi> ſpeakes of in the 23. of his Prouerbs, <hi>It goeth downe pleaſantly, but in the end thereof it will bite like a ſerpent, and hurt like a cocatrice.</hi> And as with <hi>the bread of deceipt,</hi> in the 20 of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerbs, it is at firſt <hi>ſweete to a man, but afterward his mouth ſhall bee filled with grauell.</hi> And as it is with the ſlouthfull in the ſame Chapter, <hi>The ſlouthfull will not plow becauſe of winter, therfore ſhall he beg in ſummer, &amp; haue nothing:</hi> So it is with any iniquitie, Satan drawes men vnto, he will make them belieue, they ſhall ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:14475:23"/>be ſpyed; but the truth is, that <hi>the waies of man, are before the eies of the Lord, and hee pondereth all his pathes. His owne iniquities ſhall take the wicked himſelfe, and he ſhall be holden with the coards of his owne ſinne. Pro.</hi> 5. Ioab in the 2. of Sam. 3. came to <hi>Abuer, hee tooke him aſide, in the gate to ſpeake with him peaceably, &amp; ſmote him vnder the fift ribbe, that he died.</hi> The ſame <hi>Ioab,</hi> the 20. of the ſame booke, came to <hi>Amaſa,</hi> ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>art thou in health my brother; and tooke him by the beard as though he would haue kiſſed him, but</hi> Amaſa <hi>tooke no heede to the ſword in</hi> Ioabs other <hi>hand, for therewith he ſmote him in the fift ribbe</hi> too, <hi>and ſhed out his bowells to the ground.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>He that knew <hi>Ioab</hi> had ſerued twoe ſo before, wold not truſt him (for all his complementing) to make the third, if he were any thing a prouident man. We know the Diuell doth<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> thus ſtill, what improuident men then are they, that will truſt him at all, that can thinke the Diuell meanes any man any good?</p>
            <p>You looke not I hope, for one to come from the dead, to tell you what torments, thoſe deſperat wret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches ſuffer in hell, which knowing in their life time, the Diuell would miſchiefe them, would yet needes follow him. Neither would any man here, willingly (I thinke) ſee a hand writing before him, <hi>thou art weighed in the ballance, and art found too light. Dauid</hi> himſelfe peraduenture, but that he came to him with a parable, would not haue heard ſo patiently as hee did, <hi>Nathan</hi> the Prophet ſaying vnto him, <hi>Thou art the man.</hi> It may be ſome care neither for GOD nor Diuell, <hi>if they will heare</hi> neither <hi>the Law nor the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets</hi>
               <pb n="40" facs="tcp:14475:24"/>neither Chriſt, his Euangeliſts, nor Apoſtles, neither will they heare, to any purpoſe any other. It may be ſome, if they had any feare ſtricken into the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, would thinke more awfully of God, and his proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence then euer they did. The aſmightie may ſhoote an arrowe of his hot peſtilence, at the heart of that man, if the ſtriking of others will not ſerue, that may. It may be ſome man (and hee's not the worſt) feeles his conſcience ſo griping him, for forgetfulneſſe of his dueie to God, this way many times, that he ſaies betweene God and himſelfe; I am the man, I am the man that haue ſinned, and by Gods grace doe veri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly purpoſe amendment. The beſt of vs can be no bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter minded. Then men and brethren what ſhall wee doe? What euer we haue done, let vs hereafter, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther preſume vpon gods prouidence, for our defenſe, preſeruation, and maintenance, but vſe meanes in time; no vnlawfull meanes at all, nor lawfull means vnlawfullie, wee muſt vſe them as Gods meanes, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compting them of no power without him. <hi>Except the Lord build the houſe, their labour is but loſt that build, it, Except the Lord keepe the Citie, the watchman waketh but in vain.</hi> Nor let vs put our truſt in means, as lame <hi>Aſa</hi> did to phyſitians, whereby he was noted both to diſtruſt and to diſpleaſe God. Let no man truſt in his riches, <hi>He that truſteth in his riches ſhall fall.</hi> Prou. 11. Let no man truſt to his owne wiſedome, <hi>Truſt in the Lord withall thine heart, leane not to thine owne wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome in all thy waies acknowledge him, and he ſhall direct thee in all thy waies.</hi> Pro. 3. And let vs be more thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full vnto God and man, for the happineſſe we haue,
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:14475:24"/>and haue had, eſpecially by the goſpell ſo long, ſo ſincerely, ſo freely preached, ſo ſoueraignly eſtabli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed, euen <hi>excluſiue,</hi> all other religions kept out. No nation in the world, before Chriſts time, nor ſince, till this latter age (wee in this land) euer had the like; nor at this time is there vnder heauen, the like glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous chriſtian monarchicall ſtate; which is abſolutely the beſt, <hi>O praiſe the Lord of heauen, praiſe him in the height.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And whereas, we haue obtained ſo great quietnes, and ſo many worthy things haue beene and are done vnto this nation, through the prouidence of GOD, raiſing vp mightie meanes therto, we are to acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge it, vnder God, wholie and in all places, with all thankes, to haue come, from the ſacred, noble, &amp; bleſſed gouernment of this Church and common-wealth. O that our religious thankfulneſſe and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deauors, had beene or were now anſwerable to Gods incomparable goodnes, the aboundance and excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lencie of his meanes amongſt vs. And wee muſt be more peaceable too, if wee keepe Gods order, then wee haue been manie of vs. As much as lyeth in vs, wee muſt haue peace with all men, we muſt ſeeke it, wee muſt enſue it. <hi>Bleſſed be the peacemakers, for they ſhall be called the children of God.</hi> our bleſſed Sauiours owne words in the 5. of Matth. <hi>onely by pride doth man make contention, but with the well aduiſed is wiſedome.</hi> Prou. 13. what wiſedome? <hi>the wiſedome that is from a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue,</hi> which <hi>is firſt pure, then peaceable, gentle, eaſie to be intreated, full of mercie and good fruits, without iudging, without hypocriſie. Iames.</hi> 3. But men muſt do as Gods
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:14475:25"/>ſpirit guides them; trie the ſpirit whether it bee of God, if it be, there is vnitie in it, there is peace with it, and there is a bond vpon that peace, that it be du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie kept, eſpecially the publique peace. And for pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uate wrongs done, wee muſt not bee ſo reuengefull as commonly we are, ſtriking and ſtabbing. We muſt acknowledge Gods hand in the greateſt iniuries that are done vs, and for our good if we haue grace, as <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid</hi> in the 16. of the 2. booke of <hi>Sam.</hi> beeing curſt &amp; rayled on to his face, he accompted that God had a ſtroake in it, he reuenged it not, and when an other would haue done it for him, he would not ſuffer it. when wrongs are offered vs, wee may ſeeke redreſſe by lawfull meanes, reuenge by none.</p>
            <p>Mens pointing the field, vpon their priuat quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rels, is not iuſtifiable before God, a chriſtian man can haue no ſufficient warrant for it, it is barbarous.</p>
            <p>Thou art diſgraced; it may be thou haſt deſerued it, then what wrong haſt thou? or thou haſt not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued it, thers place for patience, for charitie; but thats baſe: but thats not ſo, let King <hi>Salomon</hi> (that was thy better I am ſure) teach the. <hi>It is a mans honor to ceaſe from ſtrife.</hi> Pro. 20. <hi>and it is a mans glorie to paſſe by an offenſe.</hi> Prou. 19. <hi>and he that is ſlowe to anger is bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter then the mightie man, and he that can rule his owne minde, is better then he that winneth a Citie.</hi> Prou. 16. It is indeede a ſinfull tempting of GOD, that men without cauſe doe aduenture their liues, it argues a man diſſolutely reſolute, there's the faireſt of it.</p>
            <p>But God hath appointed euery man his end; true, therfore ſtay till it come. why that may be the time,
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:14475:25"/>and the place: yet thou mayſt be guilty of thine owne death by ſeeking it, and God may puniſh thee with final impenitencie for thy deſperatues. But thy pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe is to kill, and not to be killed. That's worſe, for then thou art guiltie of an other mans death, and thine owne too. But thou wilt fly or get thy pardon; thou canſt neuer fly from Gods preſence, &amp; though thou getteſt thy pardon for thy murther, yet thou maiſt bee damned for it: and for all thy flying thou maiſt be taken, and for all thy ſuite thou maiſt miſſe thy pardon. Then thou wilt repent, God may forgiue thee. God will not forgiue thee, vnleſſe thou very hartily repent thee, which thou art not ſure to doe when thou wilt.</p>
            <p>But thou doeſt not meane to kill, nor to be killed. Ah, thy hart faints thee; nay but thou art bold vpon thy skill, and thy iudgment: thy aduerſarie may put the beſides both: but thou knoweſt thou art too good for him; many haue made that reckoning, that haue come ſhort home. But thou haſt often tryed &amp; been tryed, and art ſafe: thanke God, and leaue there. But thou maiſt be prouoked; thou maiſt fairely, becauſe honeſtly refuſe it. But that's againſt thy nature; tell not me of thy nature, I tell thee of Gods grace, and thy duety. Say what can be ſaid, there is no proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, no well aduiſed wiſedome, no chriſtianitie in it.</p>
            <p>But can no man warrantably without tempting God, put his life in hazard? One may, if he be aſſalted when he cannot auoyd it, that's neceſſitie. If a man be at ſea vpon good occaſions, he is in his way, hee fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:14475:26"/>his vocation; or if a man be called to ſerue his Prince or Country in battaile, that's honourable. And if a man be ſet apart to ſuffer for Gods truth ſake, that's glorious.</p>
            <p>Some can be content to put vp iniuries, and to hold their liues pretious inough, but they are o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerwhelmed with ſorrowes which come vpon them whether they will or noe, for the loſſe of their goods, their friends, their children. Let them remember <hi>Iobs</hi> loſſes greater then theirs, and his patience grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter then his loſſes, in the 1. of <hi>Iob.</hi> Let them remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber what he did and what he ſaid, when his ſorrowes came one vpon anothers necke vnto him, <hi>he aroſe</hi> indeed <hi>and rent his garments, and ſhaued his head, and fell downe vpon the ground, he had ſenſe of his griefe, but he worſhipped and ſaid, Naked came I out of my mothers wombe, and naked ſhall I returue thither, the Lord haih giuen, and the Lord hath taken it, and bleſſed be the name of the Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Some are otherwiſe poore, diſtreſſed, and diſeaſed, and haue noe comfort in the world. Let them re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member <hi>Lazarus</hi> in the 16. of <hi>Luke.</hi> that liued and dyed (for this world) moſt miſer ably, but his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts after wards made amendes for all. but God was preſent at hand with them: ſo he is with vs; and can help vs, and <hi>wee knowe that all things worke together for the best to them that loue him.</hi> Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans. 8.</p>
            <p>But touching this point that God hath appointed ted euery man his end, what expreſſe ſcripture haue we for that? In the 14 of <hi>Iob,</hi> we read touching e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:14475:26"/>particular man, words thus ſpoken to God <hi>Are not his dayes determined? the number of his mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neths are with thee, thou haſt appointed his boundes, which he ſhall not paſſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If it be ſo, were it not yet better that men might know the time? why? for preparatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> againſt the time: that's ſomewhat: for it is ſeene indeed, men do pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare themſelues to death when they finde they can liue no longer, and part of their preparation is, in their affections to leaue this world, and to deſire heauen, but that's not ſo good, to be content to go, or to deſire heauen, when wee can ſtay heer no longer.</p>
            <p>The right preparation is before extremities come, conſidering the certainty, that ſuch a time will come, &amp; the vncertaintie when; ſeeing it may come at any time, men are to prepare, that they may be readie at all times. Verie fewe doe ſo; it is too true, but all ſhould do ſo. It is Gods order, our Sauiour himſelfe hath ſet it, in the 13 of <hi>Matth. Take heede, watch and pray, for ye know not when the time is,</hi> as if he had ſaid directly, the leſſe you know the ſet time, the more ought you to be alwayes in a readineſſe, by taking heede that ye be not taken at vnawares; by watching for the time, come it whenſoeuer God pleaſe: by prayer to God for grace, and mercy, grace to caſt all our care on him, mercie that he would care for vs, that whether we liue, or die, ſoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner or later, we may be the Lords.</p>
            <p>Thus much of the words, a commandement, and an inducement to obedience; the doctrine, Gods
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:14475:27" rendition="simple:additions"/>prouidence, what it is, what things are ſubiect vnto it, and Gods manner of working by it; the vſe, our being prouident, in ſetling our iudgement, in obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing Gods order, and in chriſtian practiſe. I haue in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanced in ſome particulars, you may apply it to many more. Let theſe words of my mouth, and this meditation of my heart, be acceptable in thy ſight, and effectuall in this audience, O Lord my ſtrength and my redeemer. To God the Father, God the Son and God the holy Ghoſt be aſcribed all honor, power and glory, now and for euer. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:14475:27"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
